所以第二个例子的关键教训
So the key lessons from this second example
再次涉及到6.005的大思想。
again relate to the big ideas of 6.005.
这是安全的吗？
Is this safe from bugs?
好吧，不。
Well, no.
又一次，我们发现一只潜伏的虫子抬起了它丑陋的头。
Again, we had a latent bug that reared its ugly head.
这是由于可变对象，可变日期
And it was due to the mutable object, the mutable date
反对。
object.
这个密码可以修改吗？
Is this code ready for change?
很明显，突变本身就是一种改变。
Well, obviously mutation is itself a change.
但这不是改变
But that's not the kind of change
当我们说准备好改变的时候。
we're talking about when we say ready for change.
我们的意思是程序的代码
The change we mean is whether the code of the program
不需要重写很多内容就可以轻松更改
can be easily changed without rewriting a lot of it
或者引入漏洞。
or introducing bugs.
在这里我们有两个独立的改变
And here we had two independent changes
在程序的不同部分
in different parts of the program
由不同的程序员交互
by different programmers that interacted
产生一种非常严重的虫子。
to produce a very bad bug.
现在，在这两个示例中，列表示例和日期
Now, in both of these examples, the list example and the date
这些问题本来是可以完全避免的
example, the problems would have been completely avoided
如果列表和日期是不可变的类型。
if the list and the date had been immutable types.
这些漏洞本来是设计上不可能的。
The bugs would have been impossible by design.
事实上，现代Java程序员从不使用日期。
And in fact, modern Java programmers never use date.
现在有一个班级--对不起，一个包裹
There is now a class-- sorry a package
有更好的类来表示日期
that has much better classes for representing dates
在Java中，比如ZoneDateTime，它
in Java such as ZonedDateTime, which
保证您有一个不可变的表示
guarantees that you have an immutable representation
约会的时间。
of a date time.
所以date类实际上被弃用了。
So the date class is actually deprecated.
顺便说一下，这个例子还说明了为什么可变对象
This example, by the way, also illustrates why mutable objects
可能不利于性能，因为
can be bad for performance because the simplest
避免更改任何步骤的bug解决方案
solution to the bug that avoids changing any of the steps
或者方法签名是为了春天的开始
or method signatures is for start of spring
总是返回缓存的土拨鼠答案的副本。
to always return a copy of the cached groundhog answer.
所以与其直接返回这个对象，
So instead of directly returning this object,
相反，我们创建一个新的日期来表示相同的日期
instead, we make a new date that represents the same date
时间就是那个东西。
and time as that object.
这种模式是防御性模仿。
This pattern is defensive copying.
当我们
We'll see much more of it when we
讨论抽象数据类型。
talk about abstract data types.
你可能在以前的编程中自己做过
You may have done it yourself in previous programming
就像蟒蛇一样。
like in Python.
这种防御性的复制意味着党的计划，
That defensive copy means that party planning,
表示返回此日期对象的调用方
means the caller that gets this date object back
拥有一个全新的数据对象
has a fresh data object all to itself that they can freely
在不影响这个缓存的约会土拨鼠的情况下跺脚
stomp all over without affecting this cached dating Groundhog
回答。
answer.
但是防御性复制的性能问题
But the performance problem with defensive copying
春天的开始对每一个客户都有意义吗
is that start of spring has to do it for every single client
即使大多数客户机不需要对数据进行变异。
even if most of those clients never need to mutate the data.
因此，我们可能会有很多
And we may end up, therefore, with lots
第一个春天的日期，春天价值的第一天，
of copies of first date spring, this first day of spring value,
整个记忆。
throughout memory.
如果我们改用不可变类型，
If we used an immutable type instead,
然后程序的不同部分
then different parts of the program
会在内存中安全地共享相同的值
would safely share that same value in memory
因为复制会更少，所需的内存空间也更少。
because there'd be less copying, less memory space required.
结果是不变性可以
The upshot is that immutability can
比易变性更有效率
be more efficient than mutability
因为不可变类型永远不需要进行防御性复制。
because immutable types never need to be defensively copied.
从根本上说，这里发生了什么
Now, fundamentally, what's going on here
我们有多个对可变对象的引用。
is that we have multiple references to a mutable object.
如果我们只是在本地使用它们
If we were just using them entirely locally
我们可以更容易地推理
within a method where we can reason about them more easily
或者如果我们只提到一个物体，
or if we had only one reference to an object,
我们不会有这种虫子。
we wouldn't have these kinds of bugs.
问题是多个引用
The problem is multiple references
在代码的不同部分。
in different parts of the code.
这些叫做别名。
And these are called aliases.
现在，如果你浏览一下这些例子
Now, if you walk through the examples
画一张快照图
and draw a snapshot diagram, it will be clear
我们从哪里得到这些多个参考。
where we're getting these multiple references from.
但这里有一个粗略的轮廓。
But here's a rough outline.
所以在列表示例中，相同的列表对象
So in the list example, the same list object
由两个不同的变量指向--
is pointed to by two different variables--
绝对值和方法中的列表参数
a list parameter in the sum of the absolute values method
以及main中的myData局部变量。
and the myData local variable in main.
这些变量是受控的
And these variables are controlled
不同的程序员。
by different programmers.
编写绝对值和的程序员
The programmer who is writing sum of absolute values
认为可以修改列表。
thinks it's OK to modify the list.
作为另一个程序，一个写主程序，
As the other program, the one writing main,
希望列表保持不变。
wants the list to stay the same.
但是由于别名，绝对值之和
But because of the aliases, sum of absolute values
更改列表，main的程序员就输了。
changes the list, and the main's programmer loses.
在日期示例中，有两个不同的变量名--
In the date example, there are two different variable names--
还有两个不同的变量名
also two different variable names
指向日期对象。
that point to the date object.
一个是土拨鼠的答案，这个私有静态变量
One is this groundhog answer, this private static variable
在春天的开始。
inside start of spring.
另一个是party date，这个局部变量
And the other is party date, this local variable
党内计划。
inside party planning.
这些别名在代码的不同部分，
These aliases are in completely different parts of the code,
同样，在不同程序的控制下
again, under the control of different program
可能不知道对方在做什么。
who may have no idea what the other is doing.
所以现在应该清楚了
So at this point, it should be clear
当一个方法执行变异时，
that when a method performs mutation,
在这个方法中提到这种变异是非常重要的
it's really important to mention that mutation in the method
在方法之前的注释中，
specification, in the comment before the method,
使用我们在前一篇文章中提到的结构
using the structure we talked about in the previous reading
在规格上。
on specs.
尽管如此，我们也看到，即使是在
Although, we've also seen that even when a particular method
不会改变一个对象，那个对象是可变的
doesn't mutate an object, that object's mutability
仍然可能是bug的来源。
can still be a source of bugs.
下面是一个变异方法的规范示例。
Here's an example of a spec for a mutating method.
这是效果保存。
It's effect save.
它把列表放进去--然后它改变了列表
And it puts the list-- and it changes the list
把它整理好。
to put it in sorted order.
下面是一个非变异方法的例子
And here's an example of a non-mutating method
这特别说明它返回一个新列表。
that says specifically that it returns a new list.
至少在2005年，如果效应没有明确地说
In 005, at least, if the effects do not explicitly say that
一个输入可以变异，然后在6.005中我们假设变异
an input can be mutated, then in 6.005 we assume that mutation
隐式不允许输入。
of that input is implicitly disallowed.
几乎所有的程序员都会做同样的事情。
And virtually all programmers would assume the same thing.
突如其来的突变会导致非常可怕的虫子。
Surprise mutations can lead to very terrible bugs.